<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>updates on Gud wit Wurdz - Tommie Matherne</title>
    <link>/tags/updates/</link>
    <description>Recent content in updates on Gud wit Wurdz - Tommie Matherne</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>2023, Tommie Matherne</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 13:25:14 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/updates/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Whats Next</title>
      <link>/posts/whats-next/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 13:25:14 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/whats-next/</guid>
      <description>What&amp;rsquo;s Next Here So just an update now that I&amp;rsquo;ve decided what to do with this site. This update is actually a day late from when it was supposed to go out.
That&amp;rsquo;s because on Wednesday&amp;rsquo;s I&amp;rsquo;m going to be adding updates on what I&amp;rsquo;m working on beside the tutorials, or launch a completed project. Fridays, I will be posting a tutorial akin to what was on the now defunct blog site.</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;whats-next-here&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s Next Here&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So just an update now that I&amp;rsquo;ve decided what to do with this site. This update is actually a day late from when it was supposed to go out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s because on Wednesday&amp;rsquo;s I&amp;rsquo;m going to be adding updates on what I&amp;rsquo;m working on beside the tutorials, or launch a completed project. Fridays, I will be posting a tutorial akin to what was on the now defunct blog site. It will be started all over from scratch, but with a more compact view of HTML and CSS, and with minimal set up! Following along this time will not require any installation on your computer, and can even be followed along with on your phone. The internet is amazing, ain&amp;rsquo;t it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s it, just a short update. Check in tomorrow for the set up and a look into the first steps of HTML. Fair warning, because of the more compact view of HTML that will be taken, there will be more reading and work off of this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
