<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>HTML on Gud wit Wurdz - Tommie Matherne</title>
    <link>/tags/html/</link>
    <description>Recent content in HTML on Gud wit Wurdz - Tommie Matherne</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>2023, Tommie Matherne</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 14:31:45 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/html/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Tutorial 1 Getting Started With HTML</title>
      <link>/posts/tutorial-1-getting-started-with-html/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 14:31:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/tutorial-1-getting-started-with-html/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s Go! So, here we go. The set up tutorial. If you remember the old blog about this, don&amp;rsquo;t panic. This is going to be a lot easier. Set up is streamlined a lot. In fact, we are going to get into talking about HTML in this tutorial, set up and first steps are all in one lesson now! Let&amp;rsquo;s f^&amp;amp;centkin&#39; do this!
Editor Set Up So, if you are interested in web development, I&amp;rsquo;m going to assume you have access to the internet in some fashion.</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;lets-go&#34;&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s Go!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here we go. The set up tutorial. If you remember the old blog about this, don&amp;rsquo;t panic. This is going to be a lot easier. Set up is streamlined a lot. In fact, we are going to get into talking about HTML in this tutorial, set up and first steps are all in one lesson now! Let&amp;rsquo;s f^&amp;amp;centkin&#39; do this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;editor-set-up&#34;&gt;Editor Set Up&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you are interested in web development, I&amp;rsquo;m going to assume you have access to the internet in some fashion. Thus, we are going to edit the code online. If you go to &lt;a href=&#34;www.codepen.io&#34;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;, you can sign up for free, and have at your fingertips editors with colored syntax highlighting for HTML, CSS, and JavaScript. This should open this set of instruction for everyone, whether you have a desktop, laptop, or even just your cell phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you are signed up, and signed in, of course, just click on the menu and choose &amp;ldquo;New Pen&amp;rdquo;. There you go. You are set up. The editors are separated for HTML, CSS, and JavaScript, either in separate editors available on your screen, or through tabs, depending on the size of your screen. There you are. You&amp;rsquo;re all set up. Seriously, that&amp;rsquo;s it. Why are you still here? Move on to the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;intro-to-html&#34;&gt;Intro to HTML&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important thing with learning anything with computers, from HTML to C++ to a word processor, is to play. So for today, I&amp;rsquo;m not going to cover the syntax and usage of HTML. I&amp;rsquo;m simply going to introduce the documentation and how to navigate it. After you become familiar with how the documentation is laid out, read it and play a bit. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry about the CSS and JavaScript editors in CodePen for now. Just play around with the HTML and what it does when you put it on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best documentation on the internet for HTML syntax is the Mozilla Developer Network (MDN) documents. These can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It is honestly best if you bookmark this. This reference is invaluable. Another thing to keep in mind is that the Mozilla Foundation, the folks that maintain this reference, as well as make the Firefox web browser, is a non-profit. There is no sign up, and none of your data is tracked. Because of that, Mozilla is funded through donations. If you can, please &lt;a href=&#34;https://donate.mozilla.org/en-US/&#34;&gt;donate&lt;/a&gt; to Mozilla so they can keep up their great work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to come up to speed on the documentation, if you click on the menu on your phone&amp;rsquo;s screen at the top-left (or in the left sidebar on your computer screen), you will see a section at the top that says &lt;strong&gt;Tutorials&lt;/strong&gt;. Please read through at least the HTML Basics tutorial. It is best if you can read through the entirety of the four tutorials listed, but they are very lengthy and dense, so I understand if you don&amp;rsquo;t. Just remember that they are there and come back to them when you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And don&amp;rsquo;t worry if it takes several read-throughs before you begin to understand what they are talking about. If you don&amp;rsquo;t get it, simply take notes on what is being said, plug it into CodePen, and then change it a bit to see how it affects the outcome, and finally re-read that part of the tutorial. We will go through some things in the next few weeks, but for the most part, these documents are well-written enough that I am going to trust that between reading and experimenting, you can figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, until next week&amp;rsquo;s tutorial, read through the docs, have CodePen open while you do, and experiment. Next time, we will go through some of the most frequently used tags in HTML and speak about what they do, and get to where we can get something resembling a web page up in front of us. The following week, we will cover some of the more advanced topics of attributes to tags and their effects, as well as building our first forms and tables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In week four, we move on to CSS. As you can see, this is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; fast paced. I am relying on you taking some part of the week between each post to get your hands dirty in CodePen and actually making a few shitty web pages. And yes, they are shitty. First web pages always are, especially when dealing with only HTML. Don&amp;rsquo;t fear this. We development is a creative endeavor akin to writing, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://wrd.as.uky.edu/sites/default/files/1-Shitty%20First%20Drafts.pdf&#34;&gt;shitty first drafts&lt;/a&gt; are invaluable in writing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next week, have fun, and keep learning!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
