<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Gud wit Wurdz - Tommie Matherne</title>
    <link>/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Gud wit Wurdz - Tommie Matherne</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>2023, Tommie Matherne</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 14:52:08 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Lesson 1 Command Line Starters</title>
      <link>/posts/lesson-1-command-line-starters/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 14:52:08 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/lesson-1-command-line-starters/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to the Command Line In this first lesson, I am going to make a few assumptions. You have access to a Linux command line, and know how to open it. Other than that, this is completely for a new user. Below we will take our first steps with Linux, and like any first steps, the best way to start off is by being able to orient yourself. The commands in this lesson will give you the ability to know what directory you are in, what is there, and how to go to other areas of the filesystem.</description>
      <content>&lt;h2 id=&#34;welcome-to-the-command-line&#34;&gt;Welcome to the Command Line&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this first lesson, I am going to make a few assumptions. You have access to a Linux command line, and know how to open it. Other than that, this is completely for a new user. Below we will take our first steps with Linux, and like any first steps, the best way to start off is by being able to orient yourself. The commands in this lesson will give you the ability to know what directory you are in, what is there, and how to go to other areas of the filesystem. So let&amp;rsquo;s go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-bit-about-the-prompt&#34;&gt;A bit about the prompt.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you first open the terminal, you should be met with a prompt something like this &lt;code&gt;user@host:~$&lt;/code&gt;. This is the default prompt. The anatomy of it is rather simple. The first portion identifies the &lt;code&gt;user&lt;/code&gt;, this is the logged in user, hopefully, you. After the at sign, is &lt;code&gt;host&lt;/code&gt;, or the name of the workstation (computer) that you are logged into. Linux has roots from Unix, the original multiuser and multi-machine operating system. From your desk, you may sign into any number of available servers. The &lt;code&gt;host&lt;/code&gt; portion of the name is a bit of an identifier of that legacy, and gives your computer a server name. Linux, by virtue of that Unix legacy, can be used as a server. In fact, Linux servers run more of the internet than any other kind of server operating system at 38% of all websites and 49% of the top 1,000 websites currently active according to W3Techs&#39; usage comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is the end of the identifier portion of the prompt. As is common in Linux, the separator is a colon (:). Everything after this is the actual prompt. The &lt;code&gt;~&lt;/code&gt; located here is actually the current location. &lt;code&gt;~&lt;/code&gt; is a shorthand in Linux as the user&amp;rsquo;s Home folder. If you come from a Windows background, think of this as your Users folder there. This is where you, as a user, keep your files. Other users have their own Home folders, which you may or may not be able to look into depending on the permissions that are set up on your account as well as the individual folders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One last note. Up to now, I have been using the Windows terms that should be more familiar to most readers. In Linux, though, they are called directories. The meaning is exactly the same: a filesystem organization tool to present an easy way to find files stored on the hard drive. From now on, I will be referring to them as directories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, there is the &lt;code&gt;$&lt;/code&gt; identifier. This is the active prompt. The &lt;code&gt;$&lt;/code&gt; signifies that you are using the prompt as a normal user. If you change to a root account (synonymous with superuser or administrator), the &lt;code&gt;$&lt;/code&gt; will change to a &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt; to signify that difference. After that, is the blinking cursor. Let&amp;rsquo;s put it to work, shall we?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pwd---the-where-am-i-of-linux&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;pwd&amp;rsquo; - the Where Am I? of Linux&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any time at the prompt, if you type in &lt;code&gt;pwd&lt;/code&gt; and hit enter, you will be met with a full print out of your current location. This tells you the path from filesystem root &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; (think of this as equivalent to &lt;code&gt;C:\&lt;/code&gt; in Windows), down the directory tree to your current directory. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t changed directories since opening the terminal, it should look similar to &lt;code&gt;/home/username&lt;/code&gt; with &amp;lsquo;username&amp;rsquo; actually being replaced by your user name. That is the folder that is signified by the &lt;code&gt;~&lt;/code&gt; in the prompt. I bring this one up first as it will provide some valuable context for the next few commands. There really is not much to be said about this command, so let&amp;rsquo;s move on, shall we.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-note-about-the-file-paths&#34;&gt;A note about the file paths&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of the &lt;code&gt;pwd&lt;/code&gt; command was what is known as a file path. More particularly, it is an &amp;ldquo;absolute&amp;rdquo; file path. It starts at root (&lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;), and travels past each folder name, separated by further &amp;lsquo;/&amp;rsquo; characters, and ends with a final &amp;lsquo;/&amp;rsquo; to denote that this, too is a directory. There are also a second kind of file path printing known as &amp;ldquo;relative&amp;rdquo; file paths. This is the path forward from where you are currently, on through to where you want to end up. Describing this now is a bit difficult to do with clarity. We will return to this idea shortly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ls---well-what-have-we-got-here&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;ls&amp;rsquo; - Well what have we got here?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, thanks to &lt;code&gt;pwd&lt;/code&gt;, we know where we are. But what is here? To overuse comparisons, this command line currently is a cave as black as the screen it is printed on. How do we shine a light on this? &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; is out next command to do so. Typing this command will &amp;ldquo;LiSt&amp;rdquo; the contents of the current directory, go ahead and try it out. Your output should include several items like &lt;code&gt;Desktop&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Documents&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Downloads&lt;/code&gt;, etc. These are the directories that are inside of your home directory. If you have a few that are a different color or emphasis level, those are files within this directory. Files will usually have file extensions, where directories will not. The exception to this is plain text files, which in Linux, do not require the &amp;lsquo;.txt&amp;rsquo; file extension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is pretty interesting, but the &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; command actually introduces us to a few more concepts to Linux commands: flags and &lt;code&gt;man&lt;/code&gt; pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-note-about-flags&#34;&gt;A note about flags&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you type in a &lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt; after a command, this is called a flag. Most flags are single letters, and can be preceeded with a single &lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt;. There are some flags that are entire words, though. When defining those flags, use a double flag notation (&lt;code&gt;--&lt;/code&gt;). But how do you know when you can use a flag, and what those flags are?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-note-about-man-pages&#34;&gt;A note about &lt;code&gt;man&lt;/code&gt; pages.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most, not all, commands in Linux have a MANual page that correlate to them. The help files for Linux are literally built into the system itself! To get to them, type in the command &lt;code&gt;man&lt;/code&gt;, followed by the command you want to view the man page for. In this case, let&amp;rsquo;s take a look a the man page for &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt;. Type &lt;code&gt;man ls&lt;/code&gt; at your command line now. You can use either the arrow keys or the keyboard letters &lt;code&gt;j&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;k&lt;/code&gt;. The keyboard options are known as Vi controls, we&amp;rsquo;ll touch more on that in a later lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at this page. Being able to read these pages is an important skill for us. Every page should begin with a &lt;strong&gt;NAME&lt;/strong&gt; area. This will tell you the command name, which is what you type at the command line, and usually a short line about what it does for you. After that &lt;strong&gt;SYNOPSIS&lt;/strong&gt; will give you an idea of how it is used. The &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; command can be followed by [OPTION] and [FILE]. The &lt;code&gt;...&lt;/code&gt; after each is to denote that more than one of either option can be defined. Anything marked as [OPTION] can usually be omitted.
Next is the &lt;strong&gt;DESCRIPTION&lt;/strong&gt; portion of the man page. This is where you first find a more detailed description of what the command does, as well as the options for the command. As you can tell, there are a lot of options that can be used with &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt;! Let&amp;rsquo;s just focus on two very useful ones for now, &lt;code&gt;-a&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;-l&lt;/code&gt;. Read up on those two, then press &lt;code&gt;q&lt;/code&gt; to exit the man page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;back-to-our-regularly-scheduled-program&#34;&gt;Back to our regularly scheduled program&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, back at the command line, we have a couple of things to clear up. Originally, I said &amp;ldquo;flags&amp;rdquo;, but the man pages call them &amp;ldquo;options&amp;rdquo;. This is the first instance of the time that you will see multiple names for the same thing in Linux. At least, if you don&amp;rsquo;t count the fact that a lot of people use the terms &amp;ldquo;folder&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;directory&amp;rdquo; interchangably. Hopefully, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t get too confusing, trust me, you get used to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, let&amp;rsquo;s put our findings to good use. At the command prompt, type in &lt;code&gt;ls -al&lt;/code&gt;. Yes, short code options can be strung together after a single dash (&lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt;). That is why if you are using an option/flag that is a complete word, you must preceed it with double-dashes (&lt;code&gt;---&lt;/code&gt;). Anyway, type that in and press enter and you will notice a bit more informationpresented that we need to discuss!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, there are obviously more directories. And they are all listed in a single row. AND what is with all these columns?! This is actually a more advanced way of viewing the contents of the directory you are in. It includes all folders, including hidden directories, which are revealed by the &lt;code&gt;-a&lt;/code&gt; option. The columns are a result of the &lt;code&gt;-l&lt;/code&gt; option. The first column contains a string of letters and dashes that tell you the permissions for that folder. The &amp;rsquo;d&#39; at the beginning denote it is a directory, files have a preceeding dash. Next are three sets of &amp;lsquo;rwx&amp;rsquo;, where each letter may be replaced by a dash. These mean &amp;ldquo;read&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;write&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;execute&amp;rdquo;, and are repeated three times for &amp;ldquo;User&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Group&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;Other&amp;rdquo;. We will get into what that all means in another lesson as well, for now, it isn&amp;rsquo;t important. This is followed by a number that says the number of links to that item (directory or file) exist on the entire file system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next two columns at this point will likely have your user name in both columns. These tell you what group the file belongs to, and what user in that group created the file. Again, for now, not terribly important, and we will come back to this as we get deeper into Linux administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next set of numbers is the file size measured in bytes. There are more options available that will print this in more easily digestible numbers, but you may notice now that directories are all listed as being 4096 bytes, no matter how much is contained in the directory. This is because that is just the size of the identifier that is the directory name, not the size of the contents of the directory iteself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final column before the directory name is the date and time the file or directory was last modified. Not terribly important for home use, but if you ever get a job as a cybersecurity role, this can actually be important digital forensics to note.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the names of all directories, including hidden directories. You may notice that all of the directories that now appear that were not in the original listing begin with a &amp;lsquo;.&amp;rsquo;. Believe it or not, hiding a directory or file in Linux is as simple as starting it&amp;rsquo;s name with a &amp;lsquo;.&amp;rsquo;. You may be a bit confused at the first two directories, &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;..&lt;/code&gt;. MORE LINUX SHORTHAND, YAY!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are indeed, short names for two very specific directories. &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; is simply the shorthand form of the current directory. To show this, let&amp;rsquo;s try something. The &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; command is not limited to only the directory we are currently in. If you type in a directory name after the options, you can list the contents of that directory. Let&amp;rsquo;s try it, type in &lt;code&gt;ls -al .&lt;/code&gt; with that &amp;lsquo;.&amp;rsquo; included at the end. As you can see, it repeats the same list. That is because &amp;lsquo;.&amp;rsquo; is shorthand for the directory itself. Every directory has a reference to itself built in, named &amp;lsquo;.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what about the &amp;lsquo;..&amp;rsquo;? That is a shorthand to the directory directly above the directory you are in. If you remember, when we typed in &lt;code&gt;pwd&lt;/code&gt;, we got an answer of &lt;code&gt;/home/username&lt;/code&gt;. So &lt;code&gt;username&lt;/code&gt; is our current directory, and one level above that is &lt;code&gt;home&lt;/code&gt;. If we try &lt;code&gt;ls -al ..&lt;/code&gt;, you should get a response of &lt;code&gt;username&lt;/code&gt; along with &amp;lsquo;.&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;..&amp;rsquo;. There may be more, as well, if there are other users on your Linux machine. The thing to note here, is that I mentioned every directory in Linux automatically has a &amp;lsquo;.&amp;rsquo; file referring to itself. This is also true of &amp;lsquo;..&amp;rsquo;. At first, this may not make much sense, as it would seem that there couldn&amp;rsquo;t be a &amp;lsquo;..&amp;rsquo; file for this, as there is no level higher. For &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;, the &amp;lsquo;..&amp;rsquo; shortcut simply refers back to &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; just as &amp;lsquo;.&amp;rsquo; does. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, that&amp;rsquo;s just trivia, you will never think about it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s talk briefly about one last command before we stop for the day, shall we?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cd---now-we-are-going-places&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;cd&amp;rsquo; - Now we are going places!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our next command is &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt;. If you are a curious reader, you may notice that this command doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a man page. The only reason for that is that there are no options for this command. &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; is the &amp;ldquo;Change Directory&amp;rdquo; command. By typing in &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; followed by the name of a directory, you move your &lt;code&gt;pwd&lt;/code&gt; to that directory. This brings up an important point, though. How do you have to type in the name of the directory? We mentioned earlier that the &amp;ldquo;absolute&amp;rdquo; path to our home folder was &lt;code&gt;/home/username&lt;/code&gt;, to get to, say, the Docurments directory, do we have to type in &lt;code&gt;cd /home/username/Documents&lt;/code&gt;? Well, we could. That would absolutely work. However, &amp;ldquo;relative&amp;rdquo; pathing would be much simpler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-about-relative-file-paths&#34;&gt;More about relative file paths&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is a relative file path? Simply, it is typing the name of a directory with the assumption that you are currently in the directory containing that as a subdirectory. The system will prepend &lt;code&gt;pwd&lt;/code&gt; to the path, and attempt to move there. So if you were to type in &lt;code&gt;cd Documents&lt;/code&gt; from your home directory, the system would see that as exactly the same as &lt;code&gt;cd /home/username/Documents&lt;/code&gt;. This makes typing a lot easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ever do find yourself outside you home folder, or whatever other folder you thought you were in, Linux will print out a nice error message saying that the directory you are trying to move to doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist. You can use a mixture of &lt;code&gt;pwd&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt;, to orient yourself to correct your &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; command to get where you mean to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;whew-that-was-a-lot&#34;&gt;Whew! That was a Lot!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, not really. But it was enough to get started. Look around, see what you can find. Explore your file system a bit and see what is there, and try to think about why. Knowing how your system is laid out is a very important thing for someone looking to take control of that system. Stay curious!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lesson Plan</title>
      <link>/posts/lesson-plan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2023 17:17:57 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/lesson-plan/</guid>
      <description>Linux  Command Line Basics  pwd, cd, ls, and flags mkdir &amp;amp; rmdir, rm, touch man and &amp;ndash;help cp, mv, locate   Intermediate Command Line  echo, cat, and pipes editors (vi/m, nano) sudo, df, du tar, zip, unzip uname, chmod, ping   Terminal Text Manipulation  awk, sed, grep, sort, cut, uniq, fmt, tr, nl, wc   Processes  ps, top, htop, atop, lsof kill, killall   Performance  nmon, iostat, sar, vmstat   Network  traceroute, mtr, ping, nmap, netstat, ufw/firewalld, tcpdump, iptables/nftables, dig, scp   Special Note: POSIX Bash/shell scripting  OS Admin Concepts  initd systemd virtualization/containers memory/storage file systems  Programming Setup  Hugo and Quarto Git Languages  Python R Javascript/npm    </description>
      <content>&lt;h2 id=&#34;linux&#34;&gt;Linux&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Command Line Basics
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pwd, cd, ls, and flags&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mkdir &amp;amp; rmdir, rm, touch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;man and &amp;ndash;help&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cp, mv, locate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intermediate Command Line
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;echo, cat, and pipes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;editors (vi/m, nano)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sudo, df, du&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tar, zip, unzip&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;uname, chmod, ping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Terminal Text Manipulation
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;awk, sed, grep, sort, cut, uniq, fmt, tr, nl, wc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Processes
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ps, top, htop, atop, lsof&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kill, killall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nmon, iostat, sar, vmstat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;traceroute, mtr, ping, nmap, netstat, ufw/firewalld, tcpdump, iptables/nftables, dig, scp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Special Note: POSIX&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bash/shell scripting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;os-admin-concepts&#34;&gt;OS Admin Concepts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;initd&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;virtualization/containers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;memory/storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;file systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;programming&#34;&gt;Programming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;setup&#34;&gt;Setup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hugo and Quarto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Git&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Languages
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Javascript/npm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another Switch Up</title>
      <link>/posts/another-switch-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2023 16:30:01 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/another-switch-up/</guid>
      <description>Yeah, I know I know, less focus than a 1940s film projector. This time, though, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure I&amp;rsquo;ve got the direction I actually want to go. I enjoy teaching concepts and only enough specificity to get things done. Current plan is to create a learning path series that will carry a person from first steps with Linux all the way through to building a personal project that relies on a backbone that can be transferred to real-world applications and re-created to produce actual results.</description>
      <content>&lt;h3 id=&#34;yeah-i-know&#34;&gt;Yeah, I know&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know, less focus than a 1940s film projector. This time, though, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure I&amp;rsquo;ve got the direction I actually want to go. I enjoy teaching concepts and only enough specificity to get things done. Current plan is to create a learning path series that will carry a person from first steps with Linux all the way through to building a personal project that relies on a backbone that can be transferred to real-world applications and re-created to produce actual results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This began out of a conversation with a friend saying she wishes she could do the things I do. My response, probably a bit flippantly, was to say that she could. Anyone can. The things I do for work and fun with a computer are matters of skills, not &amp;ldquo;talent&amp;rdquo;. Of course, that led to a conversation, fueled by the excellent &lt;a href=&#34;https://roadmap.sh/devops&#34;&gt;DevOps Roadmap&lt;/a&gt;, about everything that I put together in order to do these things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also made me realize, I look at that roadmap and think, &amp;ldquo;Yeah, that&amp;rsquo;s about right&amp;rdquo;. From the outside looking in, that roadmap is intimidating as hell. Eliciting thoughts of &amp;ldquo;How the hell do I learn all of that?&amp;rdquo; The short answer, though, is: You don&amp;rsquo;t!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within each section, there are solid topics to learn, but more importantly, there are concepts to grasp. In correlation with these concepts, there are tools at your disposal. So long as you can grasp the concepts, and understand the tools, you can work with them to build and do some things that are impressive. So that is what I&amp;rsquo;m going to break these things down to, concepts and tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like real tools, knowing what they are used for, and understanding how they can apply are limiting knowledge. Actually putting the tools to use are where things get interesting, and actual learning begins. You can learn the intricacies of mitre saws, laser levels, nail sizes, joinery&amp;hellip; But until you actually try to put together a table, you aren&amp;rsquo;t a carpenter. So while we will begin with concepts, very quickly, we are going to move forward to projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The projects I put forward are NOT to be followed. They are to be thought of as inspiration. To continue the carpentry comparison, think of it as someone watching an episode of The New Yankee Workshop (that&amp;rsquo;s still on, right?), and deciding they are going to build a chair that way. Their chair will be their own. You might still recognize it as an Adirondack, but it will not look the same. Some parts of construction, some design concepts in the aesthetic, and, frankly, the worksmanship of it will not match. That&amp;rsquo;s a good thing. Individualize the work. Make it your own, change what it looks like, how it works, even some underlying concepts. Take your time, do the project for you, just use the tools I give you. That&amp;rsquo;s how you learn to become a useful programmer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next time, a roadmap of what is going to happen. Please note, that roadmap isn&amp;rsquo;t finished being drawn up. It may change, it may grow, it may shrink. During each time that the articles for each part are published, the roadmap will be updated to link to them. If you want to follow along, it may be a good idea to bookmark it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick Update 2</title>
      <link>/posts/quick-update2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 17:45:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/quick-update2/</guid>
      <description>A Forced Focus So, as I admitted a bit in my previous posts, I am currently unemployed. After looking into the situation that has put me in, as well as my skills, drives, and goals for myself, it has led to a bit of a refocus for the way this site is going to go, and what that means going forward. This comes after a lot of thought with a career counselor, resume reviews, and just what I do with my spare time to keep myself from going insane.</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-forced-focus&#34;&gt;A Forced Focus&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, as I admitted a bit in my previous posts, I am currently unemployed. After looking into the situation that has put me in, as well as my skills, drives, and goals for myself, it has led to a bit of a refocus for the way this site is going to go, and what that means going forward. This comes after a lot of thought with a career counselor, resume reviews, and just what I do with my spare time to keep myself from going insane. It also caused an evaluation of what I want and need from a job going forward in order to survive and thrive. As you can tell from these themes, it is going to get a bit personal. If that isn&amp;rsquo;t your cup of tea, I understand. Please also understand, I don&amp;rsquo;t publish this to lament my lot in life, but to show others that may be in a similar position by fate and happenstance, you are not alone. It is completely okay to reevaluate life, and decide what you want and need from it. Hopefully, my process helps those folks understand that this is not a bad thing, if you find yourself needing to, evaluate your life, and make it into something more tolerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, the circumstances I lost my previous job under have some people that I have spoken to about it calling it unfair. I disagree. Those circumstances were that I was under a 90 day probation period at the job. It was laid out to me before I took the job that there was a very strict policy on missed time during that period. If I missed three days, the job was terminated. While my circumstances for missing those days were medical (I had an IBS flare up that caused severe pain, a suspected obstruction), it doesn&amp;rsquo;t change the fact that the job I undertook was a physical one in the tech field, with presence required for the business model to work. They laid that out, and I accepted, knowing my own medical history and not foreclosing that information during the hiring process. If there is anyone to blame for the job being offered and then rescinded within two weeks, it is myself, not my former employer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, it has caused me to reevaluate my life, both work and personal, when it comes to managing my illness. I have come to admit that it is, indeed, a handicap. It is not one that prevents me from working. It is just one that prevents me from leaving the house occasionally. In my job previous as a help desk analyst, I was working primarily from home. If need be, I was taking days off due to these issues when they got severe, but when it was about the same as what caused the missed days at my last job, more often than not, I would work. When need arose, I would get off the phones, and then I would return. Even on those days, despite the missed time, I was often a KPI leader in calls taken, and was seen as a bit of a leader on knowledge of the procedures and processes we were expected to follow. Lack of ability to be in office DOES NOT EQUATE to lack of ability to be a valuable team member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of that, I am going to be more up front with this disability, and admit it as such on applications. I am going to ask for flex accomodations to be able to work from home as needed to continue contributing to my work. However, I am going to limit the scope of jobs I look for in the tech field. As mentioned, the last job I had was physical. It involved running cables, installing hardware, and physically assuring system availability and operation when needed. That is not something I can reliably do. I realized that, and started, initially, looking to get back into web development, either front or back end, and slinging code. This is something I have done before. It is also something I quickly burned out on before. Not least of which because usually, the work is mainly front end that is usually desired. I have the artistic ability of a parapalegic newt, I am not the person you want implementing something that is supposed to look pretty or useful! Can I do the job? Yes. I have done it before. Same with back end, can I do it? Yes. In fact, knowledge of back end requirements, what is possible, and thinking outside the box to achieve unusual requests were one of the things that got me notied by a former co-worker that was apparently so appreciative of that skill that even six months after our last conversation, she is still giving me alerts to when new jobs come up that I can fit with where she now works. (If you see this, yet again, THANK YOU! I don&amp;rsquo;t care if you get tired of hearing that, I&amp;rsquo;ll keep saying it, because it really does mean that much.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, though, trying to put together a portfolio for that end of things reminded me, I don&amp;rsquo;t really want to have to kludge together any more bad code to fix errant requests to make systems work in ways that they shouldn&amp;rsquo;t because there was no design put into the evolution of said systems that have now grown out of spec. And let&amp;rsquo;s face it, that is pretty much the definition of back-end work. So I was left with a conundrum. Where to take my talents and skills?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began looking into what I do just because I am bored. I like baseball, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t watched a game in years. To me, part of the allure of baseball is that you don&amp;rsquo;t have to be able to watch it to be able to appreciate it. A look at the box scores can tell you, if you know how to read them, everything that happened over the course of four hours on a patch of grass, hundreds of miles away from you, among twenty or so people. A glance at a standings sheet and roster report can give you a fair idea of what will happen tomorrow among a different grouping of the same size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to games, I love to play them. Video game preferences for me run away from war and shooting, and towards simulation and stratgey. In well made strategy games, either through game menus or observational play, you get to know what situation you are in, and can formulate a plan or new goal based on the resources available to you. For simulations, the same thing arise, whether that simulation be something like SimCity, or a bit more complex, like Dwarf Fortress. Even when the numbers are hidden from view, the systems can be figured out to a degree that allows interaction with a system in a meaningful way to create situations out of seeming chaos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That has led me to thinking, data and business analytics is simply using known data to react to chaotic systems such as economy, climate change, and the unexpected in the most meaningful way possible. Do I think it will have the same fun factor as playing Dwarf Fortress, or running a Monte Carlo simulation on a possible baseball outcome? No, I&amp;rsquo;m not stupid. Work is to complete tasks for others, and to make ends meet. Play is for the other stuff. But at least with this field, I know what I&amp;rsquo;m getting into, I cannot be sold a bill of goods on changing the world, or getting rich. I&amp;rsquo;m making information more visible to make decisions more apparent, and trying to remove any possible clouds from that judgement by relating facts that may be uncomfortable. That&amp;rsquo;s not fun, but that is life, and that is something I can accept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;rsquo;s something I can do from an office, or from home. So it may just be the most perfect fit for what my life is now that I have taken a look at my life&amp;rsquo;s own data, without bias, and accepted, I&amp;rsquo;m a bit less capable than most. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t make me useless, it just makes me less of a physical presence. But I&amp;rsquo;ve already proven, I don&amp;rsquo;t have to be present to be an impact. And I&amp;rsquo;m going to make an impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, that was a lot of words, what does that mean for this site going forward? Well, for starters, while I&amp;rsquo;m not likely to do away completely with the HTML/CSS/JavaScript track, it isn&amp;rsquo;t going to be a priority. Honestly, I now the information, and know it well, but other than the JavaScript side, it just isn&amp;rsquo;t me. Those other parts are presentation, and I&amp;rsquo;m a newt, remember? I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep going with teaching, because I have quite a few transferable skills. Recently, I got involved in a study group for those breaking into data analysis and I am looking at the information on different aspects that cross over to my old jobs, and I can understand why people are frustrated thinking they can never get this. Do you really need an eight hour tutorial on database design where the first hour and a half is spent trying to clumsily define what data and a database are? Or, as a beginner, do you need just enough information to be able to take an already known-clean data set and shove it into a database in order to begin some analysis?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frankly, I think getting people up and running with the tools they need as fast as possible beats the hell out of that. You shouldn&amp;rsquo;t need to take in enough information to be an entry-level database admin in order to get up and running with entry-level data analysis. For goodness sake, if that were the case, the field is vastly underpaid! So I&amp;rsquo;m going to pivot a bit, and give a few tutorials on how to take a known clean dataset, how to evaluate that dataset in order to build the database it needs, and then import the damn thing. Then analyze it, and possibly use HTML/CSS/JavaScript to make a static page to publish a report. Then, if you are still interested, we&amp;rsquo;ll go above that and get some not so clean data, and work on the more advanced stuff. But not until we already have something to show for ourselves, dammit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until then, thanks for bearing with me through all of that. I look forward to posting again, soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorial 1 Getting Started With HTML</title>
      <link>/posts/tutorial-1-getting-started-with-html/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 14:31:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/tutorial-1-getting-started-with-html/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s Go! So, here we go. The set up tutorial. If you remember the old blog about this, don&amp;rsquo;t panic. This is going to be a lot easier. Set up is streamlined a lot. In fact, we are going to get into talking about HTML in this tutorial, set up and first steps are all in one lesson now! Let&amp;rsquo;s f^&amp;amp;centkin&#39; do this!
Editor Set Up So, if you are interested in web development, I&amp;rsquo;m going to assume you have access to the internet in some fashion.</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;lets-go&#34;&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s Go!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here we go. The set up tutorial. If you remember the old blog about this, don&amp;rsquo;t panic. This is going to be a lot easier. Set up is streamlined a lot. In fact, we are going to get into talking about HTML in this tutorial, set up and first steps are all in one lesson now! Let&amp;rsquo;s f^&amp;amp;centkin&#39; do this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;editor-set-up&#34;&gt;Editor Set Up&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you are interested in web development, I&amp;rsquo;m going to assume you have access to the internet in some fashion. Thus, we are going to edit the code online. If you go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.codepen.io&#34;&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;, you can sign up for free, and have at your fingertips editors with colored syntax highlighting for HTML, CSS, and JavaScript. This should open this set of instruction for everyone, whether you have a desktop, laptop, or even just your cell phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you are signed up, and signed in, of course, just click on the menu and choose &amp;ldquo;New Pen&amp;rdquo;. There you go. You are set up. The editors are separated for HTML, CSS, and JavaScript, either in separate editors available on your screen, or through tabs, depending on the size of your screen. There you are. You&amp;rsquo;re all set up. Seriously, that&amp;rsquo;s it. Why are you still here? Move on to the next section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;intro-to-html&#34;&gt;Intro to HTML&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important thing with learning anything with computers, from HTML to C++ to a word processor, is to play. So for today, I&amp;rsquo;m not going to cover the syntax and usage of HTML. I&amp;rsquo;m simply going to introduce the documentation and how to navigate it. After you become familiar with how the documentation is laid out, read it and play a bit. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry about the CSS and JavaScript editors in CodePen for now. Just play around with the HTML and what it does when you put it on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best documentation on the internet for HTML syntax is the Mozilla Developer Network (MDN) documents. These can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It is honestly best if you bookmark this. This reference is invaluable. Another thing to keep in mind is that the Mozilla Foundation, the folks that maintain this reference, as well as make the Firefox web browser, is a non-profit. There is no sign up, and none of your data is tracked. Because of that, Mozilla is funded through donations. If you can, please &lt;a href=&#34;https://donate.mozilla.org/en-US/&#34;&gt;donate&lt;/a&gt; to Mozilla so they can keep up their great work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to come up to speed on the documentation, if you click on the menu on your phone&amp;rsquo;s screen at the top-left (or in the left sidebar on your computer screen), you will see a section at the top that says &lt;strong&gt;Tutorials&lt;/strong&gt;. Please read through at least the HTML Basics tutorial. It is best if you can read through the entirety of the four tutorials listed, but they are very lengthy and dense, so I understand if you don&amp;rsquo;t. Just remember that they are there and come back to them when you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And don&amp;rsquo;t worry if it takes several read-throughs before you begin to understand what they are talking about. If you don&amp;rsquo;t get it, simply take notes on what is being said, plug it into CodePen, and then change it a bit to see how it affects the outcome, and finally re-read that part of the tutorial. We will go through some things in the next few weeks, but for the most part, these documents are well-written enough that I am going to trust that between reading and experimenting, you can figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, until next week&amp;rsquo;s tutorial, read through the docs, have CodePen open while you do, and experiment. Next time, we will go through some of the most frequently used tags in HTML and speak about what they do, and get to where we can get something resembling a web page up in front of us. The following week, we will cover some of the more advanced topics of attributes to tags and their effects, as well as building our first forms and tables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In week four, we move on to CSS. As you can see, this is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; fast paced. I am relying on you taking some part of the week between each post to get your hands dirty in CodePen and actually making a few shitty web pages. And yes, they are shitty. First web pages always are, especially when dealing with only HTML. Don&amp;rsquo;t fear this. We development is a creative endeavor akin to writing, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://wrd.as.uky.edu/sites/default/files/1-Shitty%20First%20Drafts.pdf&#34;&gt;shitty first drafts&lt;/a&gt; are invaluable in writing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next week, have fun, and keep learning!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Whats Next</title>
      <link>/posts/whats-next/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 13:25:14 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/whats-next/</guid>
      <description>What&amp;rsquo;s Next Here So just an update now that I&amp;rsquo;ve decided what to do with this site. This update is actually a day late from when it was supposed to go out.
That&amp;rsquo;s because on Wednesday&amp;rsquo;s I&amp;rsquo;m going to be adding updates on what I&amp;rsquo;m working on beside the tutorials, or launch a completed project. Fridays, I will be posting a tutorial akin to what was on the now defunct blog site.</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;whats-next-here&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s Next Here&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So just an update now that I&amp;rsquo;ve decided what to do with this site. This update is actually a day late from when it was supposed to go out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s because on Wednesday&amp;rsquo;s I&amp;rsquo;m going to be adding updates on what I&amp;rsquo;m working on beside the tutorials, or launch a completed project. Fridays, I will be posting a tutorial akin to what was on the now defunct blog site. It will be started all over from scratch, but with a more compact view of HTML and CSS, and with minimal set up! Following along this time will not require any installation on your computer, and can even be followed along with on your phone. The internet is amazing, ain&amp;rsquo;t it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s it, just a short update. Check in tomorrow for the set up and a look into the first steps of HTML. Fair warning, because of the more compact view of HTML that will be taken, there will be more reading and work off of this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What to Expect</title>
      <link>/posts/what-to-expect/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 17:09:56 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/what-to-expect/</guid>
      <description>COMING SOON Within the coming weeks, this site will expand greatly beyond the current static blog you are reading now. This is, after all, my portfolio! It should show this, I think, if it is going to be effective in helping me get a job.
First thing that will be done, I am going to be uploading some JavaScript games. Simple games will be the first as I gain some further familiarity with using JavaScript to make games, but gaining in complexity quickly.</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;coming-soon&#34;&gt;COMING SOON&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the coming weeks, this site will expand greatly beyond the current static blog you are reading now. This is, after all, my portfolio! It should show this, I think, if it is going to be effective in helping me get a job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First thing that will be done, I am going to be uploading some JavaScript games. Simple games will be the first as I gain some further familiarity with using JavaScript to make games, but gaining in complexity quickly. As I will be creating my own art assets, the games pages will be linking to the repositories with that art. Having no musical talent beyond karaoke (and then only in my own mind), the sound in the games will be properly credited below each game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I will be putting up more posts as were previously seen on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.blog.gudwitwurdz.click&#34;&gt;blog.gudwitwurdz.click&lt;/a&gt;. Starting with porting over those previous posts and then expanding them. If you were following that (who are you?), those posts will continue, stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, this site is currently built with Hugo using the Terminal template. Credit is at the bottom of every page if you would like to contact the creator of the template. I will be looking into creating my own template and personalizing this template, as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
